A Finding Aid to the Margueritte Kimball Papers Relating to the Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1929-1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Margueritte Kimball papers relating to the Cranbrook Academy of Art
1929-1996
Archives of American Art
Kimball, Margueritte Eleanor, 1906-1995
AAA.kimbmarg
Archival Resource Key
2 Linear feet
The papers of Margueritte Kimball, financial secretary of the Cranbrook Academy of Art, measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1929 to 1996. The collection documents the school's history through organization files collected by Kimball in her capacity as secretary, and printed material recording events at the academy.
Biographical / Historical
Margueritte Kimball (1906-1995) was a student at the Cranbrook Academy of Art in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, and served as the school's financial secretary for 26 years.
Born in Clinton, Massachusetts, Kimball graduated from Bryant and Stratton Commercial College in Boston and later took drawing classes at the Copley Society Studio. In 1941, Kimball traveled to Michigan where she visited Cranbrook, an educational complex consisting of several schools including the Cranbrook Academy of Art. She was accepted to the Academy after showing her drawings to the head of the painting department. In 1942 she began attending classes and embarked on her long career as the Academy's financial secretary. Kimball did not graduate from the school, but received an honorary degree on retirement, after which she returned to the Boston area where she died in 1995.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Organization Files, 1943-1996 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1, OV 4)
Series 2: Printed Materials, 1929-1993 (1.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-3, OVs 4-5)
Scope and Contents
The papers of Margueritte Kimball, financial secretary of the Cranbrook Academy of Art, measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1929 to 1996. The collection documents the school's history through organization files collected by Kimball in her capacity as secretary, and printed material recording events at the academy.
Organization files consist of correspondence, a file on Cranbrook's history which includes a letter from Henry Scripps Booth discussing Eliel Saarinen's association with the school, faculty and staff position charts, snapshots of people and events at the school, student rosters, Kingswood School Cranbrook yearbooks, and a sound recording of an interview with Kimball conducted by Ragnhild Reingardt. Printed materials consist of school catalogs, exhibition and sales catalogs and announcements, journals and magazines, and chronological files of mixed printed materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Margueritte Kimball in 1993. The 107 snapshots of people and events at Cranbrook were donated by John Lorence in 1993, who received them from Kimball.
Related Materials
Also in the Archives of American Art is an interview with Margueritte Kimball conducted on March 10-April 13, 1993 by Robert Brown, for the Archives of American Art, regarding her years at the Cranbrook Academy of Art.
Interviews; Sound recordings; Drawings; American studio craft movement; Administrators -- Michigan -- Bloomfield Hills; Cranbrook Academy of Art; Booth, Henry Scripps, 1897-1988; Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950; Cranbrook Kingswood School (Bloomfield Hills, Mich.)
- Organization Files, 1943-1996; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, OVs 4-5
  Scope and Contents
  Organization files contain correspondence, records of Cranbrook history including a letter from Henry Scripps Booth discussing Eliel Saarinen's association with the school, faculty and staff position charts, snapshots of people and events at the school, student rosters, Kingswood School Cranbrook yearbooks, and a sound recording of an interview with Kimball conducted by Ragnhild Reingardt.
  - Conditions of Occupancy Form for Kimball's Apartment at Cranbrook, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cranbrook History, 1951-circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes a letter by Henry Scripps Booth and an exhibition catalog both discussing the history of Eliel Saarinen at Cranbrook.
  - Exhibition Announcement Mockup, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty and Staff Position Charts for Years 1932-1969, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Interview with Kimball Conducted by Ragnhild Reingardt for "Cranbrook Memories", 1992; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sketches by Unknown Artists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Snapshots of Cranbrook Graduation Ceremony, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Snapshots of People and Events at Cranbrook, circa 1965-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of the original photographs are included in the folder along with notes by John Lorence identifying some of the people in the photographs.
  - Student Rosters, 1950-1967; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, Kingswood School Cranbrook, 1944; 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    2 yearbooks
- Printed Materials, 1929-1993; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 4
  The series consists of clippings, school catalogs, exhibition and sales catalogs and announcements, journals and magazines published by the Cranbrook Academy of Art and the Cranbrook Educational Community, and chronological files of mixed printed materials.
  - Booklets, 1982-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Catalogs, Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1973-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition and Sales Catalogs and Announcements, 1943-circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Journals, The Cranbrook Quarterly, 1975-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Magazines, The Cranbrook Magazine, 1969-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Reports, Cranbrook Educational Community, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1929-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - General, 1942-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - General, 1964-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - General, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4, Folder 2)
  - General, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)